you have a new short position in
Manulife Financial is that correct
that's correct Eric so this is a big
company let's just be clear what we're
talking about this is a well capitalized
insurer with a thirty five billion
dollar market cap that's in US dollars
forty three billion dollars in revenue
three and a half billion dollars in
annual profit
why are you short well Manulife just
concluded a trial and we expect a
verdict by the end of this year that
could have significant negative impact
on its insurance subsidiary so what's
that issue here is that Manulife s--
insurance subsidiary might be forced to
allow potentially billions of dollars of
money to flow in on 30 day you know 30
day money so very short term money and
it might have to pay a 4% or even higher
annual yield on that and this would
cause significant losses to the to the
insurance subsidiary and you know would
that could create real problems for its
capital so this is a binary outcome at
Manulife prevails at trial nothing
changes if menu' life loses and the
plaintiff wins then it could be a very
serious problem for Manulife so that's
why we're short I want to clear a couple
of things up for everybody Carson first
of all your audience knows by virtue of
experience that most of your shorts are
based on a forensic thesis right that
the company in question misstated its
financials hit damaging information or
perhaps even cooked its books you're not
saying that this is effectively an
event-driven trade correct correct
there's no element of wrongdoing here do
the one thing that that nitrogen I'm
sorry I'm glad you mentioned that
because that's really important to
emphasize that you're not saying as
unlike past positions that Manulife did
anything wrong that's correct
now there is a question whether Manulife
should have disclosed this litigation
because in the litigation itself its own
expert submitted a sworn affidavit
you know laying out how this could
really become a parade of Horrible's for
the company and it really could have
material impact but you know this really
looks to be more an issue of
incompetence from the 1990s some
policies that were underwritten back
then that nobody realized had this you
know potentially had this major error in
them and they were also underwritten at
a time when you know 4% guaranteed rate
wasn't that attractive I want to walk
through make the mechanics of the
situation again it's important that
people understand how it all works
Carson an investor as I understand it
acquired an old manual life insurance
policy that paid a gerund this is what
you're describing parent paid a
guaranteed return well above current
market rates interest rates and the
contract in theory allows the investor
to put unlimited funds into the policy
meaning that Manulife could be on the
hook
sky's the limit so to speak and that
Manulife has refused to honor the policy
and the investor has sued the company to
force it to make good on the contract is
that correct that's correct and again we
expect a decision by the end of the year
so basically the investor is a limited
partnership it is set up as a hedge fund
if it wins it's gonna seek to raise
significant money and this could
effectively make this hedge fund if it
wins the hide the highest yielding money
market type product in the developed
world so what they would do is they
would they would raise money and they
get they would stick it into this
guaranteed interest rate account that is
supposed to pay 4% now when you look at
the plain text of the insurance contract
they appear to be allowed to do this
there's no limitation on the amount of
money they could put in and there's
actually Express language that says we
will always honor this guaranteed rate
it's just nobody thought hey maybe
somebody would try to stick billions of
dollars in there in an environment in
which interest rates are really low but
it actually gets worse from Manulife
there's a second argument that the
plaintiffs are making that there
title to an annual 85 basis point or
0.85 bonus on the policy anniversary
date and that the it you know I mean
appears to be look it's not an
outlandish claim based on our reading of
the of the contract and so the
plaintiffs view is that they could put
the money in they could put a huge
amount of money in the day before the
policy anniversary date collect that 85
basis point bonus and then redeem it 30
days later and if they were to acquire
multiple contracts they could do get
that 85 basis point bonus multiple times
per year if they can acquire the same
type of contract which we understand is
is feasible so these are two separate
arguments here that they're entitled to
get 4% guaranteed rate on unlimited
money and that they can clip an
additional 85 basis points potentially
multiple times per year you described in
your report Carson which I've had a
chance to read that the worst case
scenario is a death spiral you use that
word death spiral that term for Manulife
what do you mean by death spiral sure
and to be clear that's derive from their
own expert sworn affidavit so what could
happen is that this because when when
they would put if if the plaintiff is
able to put this money in Manulife
because it's an insurance company it's
highly regulated and it's very limited
in what it's able to invest in so there
would be a negative carry there of some
sort and so that would immediately hit
earnings so Manulife would have to say
okay the you know the net present value
of this negative carry you know we
estimate as X hit earnings that reduces
capital and so they would have to then
they would have to then raise capital
and as the company so that would of
course potentially dilute MFC
shareholders but the other thing is as
the credit rating gets pushed lower than
potential policyholders would say well
you know what I'm gonna go somewhere
else for my life insurance and to be
clear there are two other life insurance
companies that could be implicated by
the same set of issues industria
Alliance and Bank of Montreal's
insurance they're all part of the same
trial but other life insurers to our
knowledge don't have that issue so when
you're trying to figure out where you
know where am I gonna feel safest
locking my money up for 30 years
potentially you would go with a higher
rated with a higher rated firm Carson
again given that this is not based on
forensic work that you've done how
confident can you be about a court case
and an outcome that has yet to be
rendered by a judge so if this were in
the u.s. we'd feel very good about the
plaintiffs chances because you know so
let me just state we are not Canadian
can't we are not Canadian attorneys we
have consulted Canadian counsel but to
our view to our mind the plain text of
the contract allows the plaintiffs
allows the hedge fund to do this and to
get the 85 basis point bonus now Canada
you guys do things a little bit
differently there it's not always up to
the plain text of the of the contract
there is a fairly recent Supreme Court
decision called sattva that might be
applicable here so we have lower degree
of confidence that the plaintiffs will
prevail in under Canadian law then we
would under US law so look we don't know
but the bottom line is it's pretty
binary if they prevail this is going to
be material for MFC and this risk is not
priced in to our view because we don't
think investors know about this
litigation